Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is י"ב Yud Bet
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 12, we pick up on י"א עמוד ב'
Yud Aleph Amud Bet and the line starts with מקנה אותן שאני,
Makne Osan Shani, it's about two thirds down. Let's see, it's about
15 lines from the bottom starting from the words מקנה
אותן Makne Osan and our learning should be in memory of my
nephew מעוז מוראל Maoz Morel זכרונו לברכה Zichrono Livracha who died defending
his troops, defending עם ישראל Am Yisrael and מדינת ישראל, Medinat Yisrael,
and תפילה Tefillah for the safe return of all of our חיילים
Chayalim and חיילות. Chayalot. Okay, so we are now in the middle
of a discussion on the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna speaks about
all of these, this פרק Perek and the next פרק Perek are
all about מציאות, Meziot, about finding lost objects. And although we started
with two people grabbing onto a lost object and arguing who found
it first, we're now dealing with other משניות Mishnayot about taking possession
of lost objects. And our משנה Mishna said that if there was
a deer running through your yard, if you said, if it was
a broken leg and you sort of said, you know, meaning that
as we'll see, you would be able to catch it, then your
field can take possession of you for the מציאה. Metziah. The משנה
Mishna actually said if you said, "let my field take possession for
me," but if it were running normally and then it really wasn't
in any way held by your field, you would not take possession.
That was the משנה. Mishna.
The גמרא Gemara began yesterday, if you remember. The גמרא Gemara began
with רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saying in the name of שמואל Shmuel
that you have to be standing alongside your field. That a field
can only and a yard can only take possession for you if
you're standing nearby it. And then the גמרא Gemara challenged this because
of another teaching that we have, that is a field that is,
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yose bar Chanina says that your yard,
your field can take possession for you,
or your yard I should say, even if you're not aware, which
presumably means if you're not standing by it. And the גמרא Gemara
made a distinction between חצר משתמרת Chatzer Mishtameret and אינה משתמרת. Aina
Mishtameret. Okay, if it is something that is protected and the things
in it will be protected and stay held and stay within the
field, then you do not need to be standing nearby. Excuse me.
If the things in it will not be protected and stay within
the field, you do need to be standing nearby. What's the reason?
What's the difference between these two? Not said clearly in the גמרא.
Gemara. רש"י Rashi says, well, because when you're standing nearby it, then
you are providing the protection, you are the one that is making
it משתמרת, Mishtameret, that is making it held. An alternative would be,
and not to ruin the surprise, we're going to get to this,
but to remind you that a day or two ago we were
looking at the difference whether a חצר Chatzer takes possession because of
יד Yad or שליחות, Shlichut,
and therefore you could obviously see a difference. If you're standing by
it, it works as יד. Yad. If you're not standing by it,
then it's not an extension of you, it works as שליחות, Shlichut,
and maybe as a יד Yad you don't need this idea of
משתמרת. Mishtameret. If it's actually being held by you, that's enough. If
it's considered physically held by you. If it's not held by you,
you need it more, a sense of under your control. But either
way, the גמרא Gemara makes this distinction
between that you
either need to be משתמרת Mishtameret or you need standing by it.
And then the גמרא Gemara went on to challenge this idea, and
it started, and
fundamentally the case we were looking at was one where you had
all of these rabbis going on a boat, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and all these rabbis, and he transferred to them ownership to the
לוי, Levi, he transferred ownership of מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who was the גבאי צדקה, Gabbai Tzedakah, he transferred
ownership of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, oh excuse me, מעשר עני, Maaser
Ani, and
he did this by renting out the space underneath which the מעשר
Maaser grain was present. So it sounds like it's a קנין חצר.
Kinyan Chatzer. And the גמרא Gemara says, what? I don't understand, he's
not standing next to his field. So isn't that, doesn't that prove
that you do not need
standing by your field in order for it to work? I should
mention also that
תוספות Tosafot points out, I don't understand, why shouldn't we just assume
that it was in his house and it was משתמרת? Mishtameret? But
he says no, maybe it's not משתמרת Mishtameret because it's not held
distinct from the other grain, so there's nothing that is going to
prevent, you know, that from being, the members of the household, that's
not off limits to them, they think it's all their house and
they're going to all just assume it's part of the rest of
the grain. So it's not really protected in any meaningful way. And
the גמרא Gemara gave two answers to this. One was to say
it's not a קנין חצר. Kinyan Chatzer. He actually transferred it by
transferring the ownership of the yard along with it transfers the ownership
of. ownership of the field along with the transfer of the ownership
of the grain. It's like a קנין אגב, kinyan agav, and then
the גמרא Gemara had a discussion about that, and the other answer
which we left up with, and this is where we continue is
אמר רב פפא דעת אחרת מקנה אותה שאני. Amar Rav Papa da’at
acheret maknah otah shani. No,
the reason there it works without him standing by it is because
somebody else is transferring it. So this idea that you need to
be standing by if it's not משתמרת mishtameret is only if you
don't is only like a מציאה metzia where you have to do
the act of taking possession all on your own. When you're the
one that has to exert totally the strength of your ownership, then
you need either משתמרת mishtameret or יד. yad. But if somebody else
is their דעת da'at is doing the transfer, your act of possession
of demonstrating possession doesn't have to be as strong, and therefore it's
okay even if it's not משתמרת mishtameret and it's not standing alongside
it. Okay, so let's see that. רב פפא אמר דעת אחרת מקנה
אותה שאני. Rav Papa amar da'at acheret maknah otah shani. When another
intent, when another דעת da'at is transferring it, that's different. ומנא תימרא?
U-mena teimra? Where do I get this idea from that that lowers
the demands of what you are required for your מעשה קנין ma'aseh
kinyan if somebody else is actively doing the transfer? דתנן, De-tenan, because
our משנה Mishnah says רצו רצים אחר מציאה, ratzu ratzin achar metzia,
that you saw people running after this deer and if the deer
has a broken leg and it's in your yard, you can take
possession of it before they do. ואמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי יוחנן
והוא שרץ אחריהן ומגיען. Ve-amar Rabbi Yirmeyah amar Rabbi Yochanan ve-hu she-ratz
achareihen u-magian. And רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah says in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that what the משנה Mishnah is really getting
at, whether it has a broken leg or not a broken leg,
that's really not significant. What's significant is whether you are able to
grab it before it leaves your field. And if you are, then
it is considered to be saved, held within your field if it's
something that you can seize. Okay, so that's just explaining the difference
between the broken leg and the not broken leg. ובעי רבי ירמיה.
U-ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeyah. And רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah asked במתנה היכי? be-matanah
heichi? What would be the story if I wanted to transfer to
you my deer as a gift and it was running through your
yard? Would it require that you be have a דעת da'at that
you be able to seize it before it got out of the
yard? וקיבלה מיניה רבי אבא בר כהנא. Ve-kiblah minei Rabbi Abba bar
Kahana. And רבי אבא בר כהנא Rabbi Abba bar Kahana understood from
this question that he wanted to make a distinction and he understood
אף על פי שאין רץ אחריהן ומגיען. af al pi she-ein ratz
achareihen u-magian.
Even if you try to run after them and you can't seize
it, if somebody is giving it to you as a gift, that
suffices. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? What's the only difference
here between a מתנה matanah and a מציאה? metzia? לאו משום דדעת
אחרת מקנה אותה שאני? Lav mishum de-da'at acheret maknah otah shani? It
must be that when somebody else transfers it, that's what makes the
difference. Okay, so when there's more an active act of being transferred
by the other side, your act of possession doesn't need to be
as strong. So where are we here? We're saying that חצר chatzer
works to be קונה koneh even if it is not משתמרת mishtameret
and you're not standing by it, and the thing is running through
and will escape. It doesn't matter if somebody else is מקנה makneh
it to you, is they're intending to give it to you and
that's what they're trying to do, then it's okay to even hold
it loosely and that works. If you have a מציאה metzia though,
the claim is you need one of two, either משתמרת, mishtameret, right,
or you need עומד בצד שדהו. omed betzad sadehu. Okay, and that's
what we're discussing. Now,
right, okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה
רב שימי לרב פפא. Amar leih Rav Shimi le-Rav Papa. רב שימי
Rav Shimi said to רב פפא. Rav Papa. הרי גט דדעת אחרת
מקנה אותה
שאני. Harei get de-da'at acheret maknah otah shani. What do you mean?
By גט, get, the husband is the one that is transferring ownership
to the wife, especially because he can do it even against her
will. So not only is he willing to transfer it, meaning it
is his will to transfer it and you have דעת אחרת מקנה,
da'at acheret maknah, sometimes it's only his דעת. da'at. Okay, ואמר עולא
והוא שעומדת בצד ביתה או בצד חצרה. Ve-amar Ulla ve-hi she-omedet be-tzad
beitah o be-tzad chatzerah. And עולא Ulla says
that if you want גט get to work by putting it into
her yard, she has to be standing nearby it. All right, and
it's not enough that
דעת אחרת da'at acheret doesn't work,
it doesn't suffice and you still have these requirements of משתמרת mishtameret
or standing by.
Actually, by the case of בית bayit it sounds like you need
both, both משתמרת mishtameret and standing by. So let's take a look.
No, שאני גט דאיתיה בעל כרחה. shani get de-iteih be-al karchah. גט
Get is different. Since it can be forced on her, we need
more of a sense of her taking possession. Now why does that
exactly make sense? But somehow maybe it's if he's doing it all
and she's not trying to take possession, so therefore her act of
being possession has to be stronger. והגמרא Ve-ha-gemara actually questions why it
would go necessarily in this direction.
מתקיף לה רב ששת בריה דרב אידי. Matkif lah Rav Sheshet bereih
de-Rav Idi. רב ששת Rav Sheshet son of רב אידי Rav Idi
challenged this. ולאו קל וחומר הוא? ve-lav kal va-chomer hu? What do
you mean? It's a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה גט דאיתיה בעל
כרחה, u-mah get de-iteih be-al karchah, a גט get that you can
force on her that she's not willing to. willingly participating in, אי
עומדת בצד ביתה ובצד חצרה אין אי לא לא, i omedet be-tzad
beita u-ve-tzad chatzera in i lo lo, it only works if she's
standing by, if there's a strong קנין kinyan on her end, you
know, it's a strong demonstration of ownership.
מתנה דמדעתא, Matana dim’da’ata, a gift where she is, where it requires
her דעת, da'at, לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Isn't it certain?
Now, how do these arguments work both ways? So the argument that
you would make more of a demand by גט get makes a
certain degree of sense because, you know, it by the case because
then you would have the husband's דעת, da'at, but you don't have
the wife's דעת, da'at, at least in a case when it's בעל
כרחה. be-al korchah. Maybe there are times you do. But let's at
least take the like that that that can be the scenario. So
if you don't have her דעת, da'at, maybe she needs a stronger
מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan and she has to be עומדת בצד ביתה.
omedet be-tzad beita. That's presumably what the גמרא Gemara meant initially, that
maybe it was only a requirement by גט. get. Here the גמרא
Gemara is sort of saying the opposite, that if a גט get
is something that it's the husband is so empowered that he can
force it on her, something we find nowhere else, right? So the
תורה Torah is strengthening the ability for him to give it to
her and is sort of disregarding, you know, her role in it
and she's very much, you know, being like being like an object
here and not an equal subject, then it makes sense that it
would also make it easier for her to give it to her
even if she's not standing by the field. So certainly then if
we still require it there, we should certainly require it by a
normal מתנה. matana. Anyway, you could go either way by a גט,
get, but now the גמרא Gemara is going to be clear about
why גט get is different. אלא אמר רב אשי Ella amar Rav
Ashi and this is a very clarifying גמרא Gemara about the significance
of of עומד בצד שדהו omed be-tzad sadehu or בצד... חצר אישתרי
ביה משום יד ולא גרע משליחות. Chatzer ishtari beh mishum yad ve-lo
gara mi-shlichut. Going back to our whole discussion before of whether חצר
chatzer is משום יד mishum yad or משום שליחות. mishum shlichut. He
says it's both. Okay, it can function as a יד, yad, but
even if it can't function as a יד, yad, it functions as
a יד, yad, but even if it doesn't function as a יד,
yad, it's not worse than a שליח. shaliach. Minimally it's a שליח.
shaliach. But there are times that it can even be a יד.
yad. Which what defines it? Whether you're עומד בצד. omed be-tzad. If
you're standing in it, then it's an extension of you. Otherwise, it's
operating on your behalf. גבי גט דחוב הוא לה, Gabi get de-chov
hu lah, by a גט get that it's to her detriment and
our principle is אין חבין לאדם אלא בפניו, ein chavin le-adam ella
be-fanav, that you cannot do some that the whole idea, why do
we say your field can take possession for you even if you're
not aware? Because if it's an idea of שליחות, shlichut, we would
say, you know, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. zachin le-adam she-lo be-fanav. ראובן,
Reuven, if I wanted to give a gift to שמעון Shimon and
שמעון Shimon isn't around, I can give it to ראובן Reuven and
ראובן Reuven can, you know, take possession for שמעון, Shimon, זכין לאדם
שלא בפניו, zachin le-adam she-lo be-fanav, because he's only helping out שמעון.
Shimon. If he sees a מציאה, metziah, he can pick it up
for שמעון. Shimon. That's מגביה מציאה לחבירו, magbi’ah metziah le-chavero, he's helping
out שמעון, Shimon, except maybe he's hurting other people. Okay, which but
that we'll get to. And that we've also seen and discussed. Okay,
but that's זכין. zachin. But when something is to שמעון's Shimon detriment,
okay, ראובן Reuven can't act on שמעון's Shimon behalf if he's not
designated. So a חצר chatzer cannot act as a שליח shaliach in
the case of a גט. get. And also the woman can't say,
here I am, I'm ממנה memaneh my חצר chatzer a שליח shaliach
for a גט. get. Okay, a חצר chatzer is not a real
person to be designated as a שליח. shaliach. But the תורה Torah
is not going to have a חצר chatzer function on the woman's
behalf if it's to her detriment. Okay, so therefore, since the category
of גט get is seen as being to her detriment—meaning even in
a particular case where she wants it, you know, she's losing the
rights that she gets from marriage and so on, so it's a
category that is seen as being to her
detriment—so חצר chatzer does not function as her שליח. shaliach. אין חבין
לאדם אלא בפניו. Ein chavin le-adam ella be-fanav.
So therefore,
that's why by גט, get, that's why even if it's משתמרת, mishtameret,
like her house, she has to be עומדת בצד ביתה, omedet be-tzad
beita, because there it has to be like you are putting, if
you're putting it on her person or in a חצר, chatzer, her
house, which is considered an extension of her if she is in
it, if it's יד. yad. So by by גט, get, which is
a which is to her detriment, it only works as יד yad
and she has to be עומדת בצד שדהו. omedet be-tzad sadehu. Okay,
מתנה
דזכות הוא לה, Matana de-zechut hu lah, but מתנה matana which is
somebody's benefit, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. zachin le-adam she-lo be-fanav. That you
can do you know, that works even as a חצר, chatzer, even
as a even as a שליח, shaliach, even if you're not עומד
בצד. omed be-tzad. So now we have three categories: גט, get, even
with משתמרת, mishtameret, you need עומד בצד omed be-tzad to function as
a יד. yad.
By a מתנה matana and
מציאה, metziah, it might be able to work as a שליח. shaliach.
But within מתנה matana and and מציאה, metziah,
there's a difference. Okay, by מתנה, matana, which is דעת אחרת מקנה,
da’at acheret makneh, you don't need to be עומד בצד omed be-tzad
and you don't even need it to be משתמרת, mishtameret, because and
that's דעת אחרת מקנה, da’at acheret makneh, that's by a מתנה. matana.
When you have דעת אחרת מקנה, da’at acheret makneh, even a loose
holding on to it is enough. And by a מציאה, metziah, you
need a stronger holding on to it, so by a מציאה, metziah,
you need either משתמרת, mishtameret, like it's actually, you know. go to
be held
because it's protected or you need עומד בצד. Omeid Batzad. Whether עומד
בצד Omeid Batzad by a מציאה Metzia works as יד Yad or
works as a type of a משתמרת, Mishtameres, that's not clear. All
right? So by גט Get you always need עומד בצד, Omeid Batzad,
by דעת אחרת מקנה Da'as Acheres Makneh you don't need either משתמרת
Mishtameres or עומד בצד, Omeid Batzad, and by מציאה Metzia you need
either משתמרת Mishtameres or עומד בצד. Omeid Batzad. All right. Remember that,
that's going to be on the test. Anyway, the interesting thing I
should have mentioned before we move on is that the משנה, Mishnah,
what do you call it? The משנה Mishnah says that if the
person says let my field be קונה Koneh for me. And in
all these cases we've been saying that חצרות קונה שלא מדעתו, Chatzeiros
Koneh Shelo Mida'ato, you don't even need to be intentional. So תוספות
Tosfos basically says no, it doesn't really mean you have to say
it.
But anyway, that's a little bit strange, the משנה Mishnah says that
you actually like did say it. And you know, maybe you could
think about distinguishing between cases, between משתמרת Mishtameres on the one hand,
maybe משתמרת Mishtameres you don't have to say it, maybe אינה משתמרת
Eina Mishtameres but עומד בצד Omeid Batzad you do have to say
it, but it's interesting that the משנה Mishnah says you have to
say it and that's sort of been completely bracketed in all of
this discussion. Okay, so let's take a look now as the גמרא
Gemara continues.
גופא, Gufa, four lines from the top of י"ב עמוד א'. Yud
Beis Amud Aleph. ראה את המציאה רץ אחר מציאה, Ra'ah es hametzia
ratz achar metzia, אמר ר' ירמיה אמר ר' יוחנן והוא שרץ אחריהן
ומגיען. Amar Rabbi Yirmeya Amar Rabbi Yochanan vehu sheratz achareihem umagi'an. Only
if you can run after them and capture them. That's what we've
been saying, that's the significance of the broken leg. בעי רבא, Ba'ei
Rava, זרק ארנקי בפתח זה ויצא בפתח אחר מהו? Zark arneki bepesach
zeh veyatza bepesach acher mahu?
Let's say you threw a wallet
through one window and it was flying and it was heading out
through the other window.
Okay, that's like the deer that's running through that you can't capture
it. All right. אויר שאין סופו לנוח כמנוח
דמי או לא? Avira she'ein sofo linu'ach kemunach dami o lo? If
it is not going to land in that, it's just passing through.
Is that like it's in your yard, in your airspace for you
to consider to be able to capture it and would it work
for a קנין? Kinyan? אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא, Amar lei Rav
Pappa leRava, Rav Pappa said to Rava, ואמרי לה רב אדא בר
מתנא לרבא, Ve'amrei lei Rav Adda bar Matna leRava, ואמרי לה רבינא
לרבא. Ve'amrei lei Ravina leRava. So somebody said to Rava, לאו היינו
מתניתין, Lav hainu matnisin, isn't this our משנה? Mishnah? ראה את המציאה
רץ אחר מציאה, Ra'ah es hamatze'ach achar metzia, that if you saw
them running, ואמר ר' ירמיה אמר ר' יוחנן והוא שרץ אחריהן ומגיען,
Ve'amar Rabbi Yirmeya Amar Rabbi Yochanan vehu sheratz achareihem umagi'an, that only
if you can capture them. So that would mean if it was
like a מציאה Metzia wallet flying in and you couldn't run and
catch it in mid-air it wouldn't work. But also your case that
somebody intentionally threw it in sounds like somebody wants to transfer it.
ובעי ר' ירמיה, U'ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeya, and Rabbi Yirmeya asked במתנה היכי,
Bematanah heich, what would be the story by a gift? וקבלו מיניה
דאבא בר כהנא במתנה אף על פי שרץ אחריהן ואין מגיען. Vekiblu
minei de'aba bar Kanna bematanah af al pi sheratz achareihen ve'ein magi'an.
And it was basically and that was understood to mean that if
it was a מתנה Matanah and if it was דעת אחרת מקנה
Da'as Acheres Makneh you don't have to be able to capture them.
So how is this any different than the principle that we've just
been teaching that if it's a מתנה Matanah you don't need משתמרת
Mishtameres and even something flying through your yard, even a deer running
through your yard should be good by a מתנה, Matanah, so the
same with a wallet that's flying through your yard.
So אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back, מתגלגל קאמרת? Mitgalgel kamarta?
What, something that's rolling through your yard? שאני מתגלגל כמנוח דמי. Shani
mitgalgel kemunach dami. If it's rolling, then it's sort of like present.
Okay? If it's flying through the airspace, it can maybe it can
never even be said to be in your yard. If something is
falling into your airspace and it's going to hit your ground, then
you're קונה Koneh it as soon as it reaches your airspace. But
if it's flying through your airspace, you know, and it never touches
the ground, it cannot be said to be in your yard. So
there's different levels. Flying might not be in your yard at all
as opposed to falling into your airspace and going to land. Rolling
through your yard, space, running through your airspace, I mean he says
it's like it's stationary. It's not exactly stationary. There's an issue of
whether it's being held or not held. So we can
discuss are you being held, but it certainly is present in your
yard and therefore דעת אחרת מקנה Da'as Acheres Makneh it would suffice.
So a lot of interesting
different distinctions that are going on
here. Okay, let's keep on going and take let's take a look
at the next
משנה. Mishnah. מציאת בנו ובתו הקטנים. Metzi'as beno uvito haktanim. So again
as we said, we're all dealing with different cases of מציאה. Metzia.
Until now a lot has been taking possession of a מציאה, Metzia,
debating who found it, falling on it, running through your yard. Okay,
now somebody else finding a מציאה, Metzia, is it yours or is
it theirs if there's somebody that's part of your
household? מציאת בנו ובתו הקטנים Metzi'as beno uvito haktanim if your son
or daughter that are under age find something. מציאת עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים
Metzi'as avdo veshifchaso hakenanim if your Canaanite slaves, your non-Jewish slaves find
something. מציאת אשתו Metzi'as ishto if your wife, obviously we're talking about
a man, finds something. הרי אלו שלו. Harei elu shelo. You keep
them. Now why do you keep it? Okay, for your wife, that's
part of the sort of
reciprocal rights and responsibilities that the rabbis set up in marriage that
says a husband is going to have a responsibility... he was the
breadwinner, he has responsibility to house and to feed and to provide
clothing and an allowance for his wife and all of that, and
in exchange, if she earns any money it goes to him, and
if she finds anything, you know, it also goes to him. Okay,
other types of things he's responsible for: burial, health costs, a whole
range of things, but because of this, things she earns or finds
go to him. Now, you know, the גמרא Gemara also allows her
to stipulate against that and her to keep her own earnings, that's
a whole separate conversation. That's the wife. Daughter, you know, a father
basically has rights to, בבית אביה, beveit aviya, רש״י Rashi says, has
rights in his underage daughter, so much to the point that he
can sell her as a slave or marry her off as a
wife. תוספות Tosafos says that it's this aspect about getting the מציאה
metzia really more rabbinic, you know, that there should be a good
relationship between the father and the daughter because you don't want him,
her to have found like, you know, a nice diamond and keep
it to herself and then he's going to be really angry and
he's going to misuse his power and abuse his power and go
ahead and marry her off or sell her off to somebody that
would be to her detriment. Okay, but as opposed to, and the
slaves, you know, the slaves are considered like your property, they are
totally an extension of you, and therefore if they take possession of
something, that's sort of like the חצר chatzer or the יד yad
that we've been discussing about before. The one case that is not
clear is your underage son, and that will be discussed in the
גמרא. Gemara. מציאת בנו ובתו הגדולים, Metziat beno uvito hagedolim, your adult
children, מציאת עבדו ושפחתו העברים, metziat avdo veshifchato haivrim, your Hebrew slaves,
which you don't own, you have just the rights to their earnings,
מציאת אשתו שגירשה אף על פי שלא נתן כתובה, metzias ishto shegeirasha
af al pi shelo nasan kesuva, the findings of if your wife
finds a lost object once you've divorced her even if she doesn't
have the כתובה, kesuva, the fact that, meaning the כתובה kesuva meaning
the lump sum payment that you pay at the time of divorce,
even if that hasn't been paid, that does not mean once she
is divorced those whole reciprocal rights and responsibilities stop, הרי אלו שלהן,
harei elu shelahen, they get to keep it. And the גמרא Gemara
will discuss the issue about the slave, the Hebrew slave, because you
might be asking yourself if even a hired hand you keep their
מציאה, metzia, which we discussed before, שכיר, sachir, certainly a Hebrew slave,
you know, where you own the rights to their labor, certainly you
should get, so that will be discussed in the גמרא Gemara as
well. Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר שמואל,
Amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, מפני מה אמרו מציאת קטן לאביו? mipnei
mah ameru metziat katan leaviv?
Why did the rabbis say in this משנה Mishnah that if a
minor boy finds something it goes to the father? Everything else makes
sense, why it goes to the husband, owner, father, but why by
a minor boy? שבשעה שמוצאה מריצה אצל אביו ואינו מאחר בידו, shebeshaah
shemotzaah miritza etzel aviv veeino meacher beyado,
that the moment he finds it he says, "Daddy, daddy, look what
I found," and he doesn't hold it into his hand, which means
that he basically never picks it up for his own possession. Now,
I don't know about שמואל, Shmuel, but that's not my experience necessarily.
Kids find something, they assume they're going to keep it and it's
theirs. But that's what he says. Okay? So therefore he really never
has any דעת daas to be קונה koneh it. So the גמרא
Gemara says, למימרא דסבר שמואל קטן לית ליה זכייה לנפשיה מדאורייתא? lomeimra
desavar Shmuel katan leit lei zachiya lenafsheih mideoraisa? Does that mean that
שמואל Shmuel thinks that a קטן katan never really owns anything for
his own as a biblical matter? He always, you know, his intent,
meaning not that he doesn't have the legal ability, that also can
be asked: since when do we think minors have the legal ability
to take possession of something? We'll get to that. But here, because
of the fact that he always shows it to his father, in
practice he never takes possession of anything. Is that really true as
a biblical matter? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, השוכר
את הפועל ילקט בנו אחריו, hasocher es hapoel yelaket beno acharav, למחצה
לשליש ולרביע לא ילקט בנו אחריו. lemachetza leshlis uleravia lo yelaket beno
acharav.
If somebody is hiring a worker to go into the field and,
you know, to pick up the pick up the grain, then stuff
that the grain that's been harvested... I own the field and I
hire ראובן Reuven and, you know, people have harvested, have cut down
the grain and I hire ראובן Reuven to go ahead and to
bundle it up and to, you know, make it into sheaves. So
if you remember מגילת רות, Megillat Rus, then people can come after
ראובן Reuven and pick up the things he dropped, and that's לקט,
leket, that's gathering the things that are dropped. If ראובן Reuven is
a poor person, which usually will be the case, is he allowed
to go ahead and to hire his children to go ahead and
to pick up the grain that he dropped and they'll be taking
it because of לקט? leket? Now of course you might want to
wonder won't that lead him to drop more than he would normally
drop, but that's not the concern here. Okay. So it says, so
what does it say? It says that he may do that, ראובן
Reuven may have his children do that.
However, למחצה לשליש ולרביע לא ילקט בנו אחריו. lemachetza leshlis uleravia lo
yelaket beno acharav.
If however
ראובן Reuven is a sharecropper and he gets, you know, a portion
of the produce, then he cannot have his child collect the grain
that he drops. Why? Because even if רש״י Rashi says he's an
עשיר, ashir, but even if he's not an עשיר, ashir, even if,
you know, because he has a possession of the field, even if
that would not be enough to make him an עשיר, ashir, the
הלכה halacha is the owner of the field, even as an
עני, ani, is prohibited from going and
And the assumption is that when the son collects, he's collecting on
behalf of his father, and therefore as the owner of the field,
he cannot be the one to collect the grain. Okay, but in
the first case, even if he's collecting on behalf of his father,
his father is an עני, oni, and therefore he can have his
child collect for him. So that scenario makes it pretty clear that
when a child, and presumably here we're talking about under age, when
a child and a son collects for, you know, picks up a
מציאה, metzia, which is what לקט leket effectively is, it's free for
the עניים, aniyim, it's a מציאה, metzia, anybody can come get it,
that it becomes the possession of the father, and that's okay therefore
if the father is just a day laborer, but not if the
father is a partial owner of the field because he is doing
it as a sharecropper. רבי יוסי אומר Rebbi Yosei Omer נמר, namar,
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei says בין כך ובין כך ילקטי בנו ואשתו
אחריו, beinkah u’veinkah ilaketi beno veishto achrav, either way the son can
do it because the son or his wife are taking possession for
themselves and therefore even if this guy is considered a part owner
of the field, the son and the wife are still עניים aniyim
and it's not being collected for the father, it's being collected for
them and therefore it works. Okay, but why is that a problem?
The first opinion seems to go like שמואל. Shmuel. It's a problem
because of the next line. ואמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי, Ve’amar Shmuel
halacha keRebbi Yosei, we rule like רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosei. So it
sounds like from רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei that the child does take
possession for himself and it doesn't go directly to the father. All
right, now I'm going to pause for a moment, the גמרא Gemara
is not going to discuss אשתו, ishto, but I'll pause for a
moment to explain that because you might be thinking and the משנה
Mishna also says that you know if a wife finds something it
goes to her husband. But here's the difference. The question is how
does it get transferred? By the wife owning something conceptually she takes
possession and then the rabbis said we're going to transfer that ownership
of that object to the husband in exchange because the husband provides
other things for the wife. Since initially she's taking possession, in this
case let's say where the guy's a sharecropper, even though he doesn't
have a right to collect the grain that he dropped, she as
a poor person does collect it and then after she collected and
owns it conceptually then it transfers to him. Okay, and you could
say the same by the minor and you could say it in
the משנה. Mishna. The minor takes possession first, a poor person is
taking possession of the grain, and then it transfers to the guy
who is the sharecropper and that would actually work. But according to
שמואל Shmuel that it never first goes to the minor, it always
goes straight to the father, how can you rule like רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yosei that it's okay for the minor in the case of
the sharecropper to pick up the לקט? leket? Okay, so let's take
a look. אי אמרת בשלמא קטן אית ליה זכייה לנפשיה, Iy amart
bishlama katan islei zechiya lenafshei, if you say that a קטן katan
it's you know first the possession goes to himself, it starts with
himself,
כי קמלקט לנפשיה קמלקט ki kamlaket lenafshei kamlaket then he's owning it
himself even if afterwards conceptually even if it's like the same moment
in time but conceptually afterwards it gets transferred over to the father.
ואבוה מיניה קזכי, V’avuh minei kazachi, the father gets it from him,
if for whatever reason חז״ל Chazal said like they said by a
minor girl, a minor boy, once he takes possession it goes to
the father. Fine, but first it started with his and he's allowed
to do it because he's a minor, because he's an עני. oni.
Okay, אלא
אי אמרת קטן לית ליה זכייה לנפשיה, ela iy amart katan leislei
zechiya lenafshei, but if like שמואל Shmuel said that when he picks
it up he's never intending to pick it up for himself, he's
only picking it up for the father, so כי קמלקט לאבוה קמלקט.
ki kamlaket la’avuh kamlaket. So therefore the קטן katan never owned it,
the father owns it either through the קטן’s katan’s picking it up
like מגביה מציאה magbiya metzia or because when it gets into the
hands of the father, the father takes possession. So אבוה עשיר הוא.
avuh asher hu. So the father is rich, you know effectively rich,
he's a part owner of the field, he's not allowed to take
directly possession of the לקט. leket. אמאי אשתו ובנו מלקטין אחריו, Amai
ishto uveno melaktin achrav, why would that be permissible? Okay, so this
shows that at least according to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei who שמואל
Shmuel פסקנס paskens like, that even if the father gets the מציאה
metzia of the wife and the child, or let's say the child
focus on that, it first goes to the child and then gets
transferred to the father, not the mechanism that שמואל Shmuel said.
So the גמרא Gemara says שמואל טעמא דתנא דידן קאמר ולאו ליה
סבירא ליה. Shmuel ta’ama detanna deidan ka’amar velo leh sephira lei. שמואל
Shmuel is explaining what he thinks is going on in the משנה,
Mishna, not his own opinion. Now of course that's a little bit
bizarre. If he holds that there is a mechanism that it goes
to the child and from the child to the father then why
didn't he explain that that was what was going on in the
משנה? Mishna? Why did he make up this whole other reason of
what was going on in the משנה? Mishna? And תוספות Tosfos discusses
that and maybe we'll touch back on that in a minute. But
anyway שמואל Shmuel yes there's two ways to understand the משנה, Mishna,
שמואל Shmuel personally holds first child then father, first son I should
say then father, in the משנה Mishna he thinks it's going straight
to the father. Okay, וסבר רבי יוסי
קטן אית ליה זכייה מדאורייתא, v’savar Rebbi Yosei katan islei zechiya midioraisa,
now does רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosei, remember רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei is
the one that says in the case of. of לקט Leket goes
to the father and after the father it goes to the son
and after the son to the father. Does רבי יוסי Rav Yose
really hold that? ותנן V'tannan didn't we taught in a משנה Mishnah
מציאת חרש שוטה וקטן יש בהם משום גזל מפני דרכי שלום Metzi'as
cheresh shoteh v'katan yesh bahem mishum gezel mipnei darchei shalom that if
a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan people that are not considered
to be of you know of of like agents in the law
either because they're not old enough or because they're not considered to
have full דעת da'as full you know which is a whole separate
conversation anyway technically they should not be able to take possession of
something without דעת אחרת מקנה da'as acheres makneh and that's a point
we discussed earlier today. If somebody else is trying to transfer something
it might be different. But a מציאה Metzi'ah they don't have enough
דעת da'as that they can take possession on their own. Okay and
therefore the only reason if they find something a lost object you're
not allowed to take it is דרכי שלום darchei shalom we want
it to be a nice running society so we say you know
let them keep it but technically they really did not do an
act of a legal act of taking possession. That's what the משנה
Mishnah says. רבי יוסי אומר גזל גמור. Rav Yose omer gezel gamur.
No it really is real stealing. Well okay that sounds like what
we just said that רבי יוסי Rav Yose says you can take
a minor can take full possession in the case of the לקט.
Leket. Okay but רבי יוסי Rav Yose is going to now be
qualified. ואמר רב חסדא גזל גמור מדבריהם. V'amar Rav Chisda gezel gamur
midivreichem. No no no rabbinically it's considered גזל. gezel. It's גזל gezel
because of דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. So what difference does it make
if you say it's don't it's theirs because of דרכי שלום darchei
shalom or it would be stealing from them because of דרכי שלום?
darchei shalom?
So ואמר רב חסדא v'amar Rav Chisda רב חסדא Rav Chisda said
I just did that
נפקא מינא להוציאה בדיינים. nafka mina l'hotzia b'dayanim. The question is that
if somebody went ahead and violated the דרכי שלום darchei shalom and
took it from them would they now be able to sue and
get it back? According to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma it was
just like no the rule is don't take it from them but
if you violated the rule in the end it really wasn't theirs.
ורבי יוסי v'Rav Yose says no no no because of דרכי שלום
darchei shalom we're going to make a rule that's going to say
they own it. Okay and therefore if somebody takes it they can
sue and get it back. Fine. So now we see though that
he does say that that they own it but it's because of
דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. And the גמרא Gemara feels and it's not
exactly clear why that that would not be good enough in the
case of the לקט. Leket. That since it's not דאורייתא de'Oraisa since
it's only דרכי שלום darchei shalom or maybe we could add you
know it's the if the דרכי שלום darchei shalom is the motivator
that's different than establishing a fundamental idea that a minor can do
a קניין. kinyan. All right so either because it wants it to
be a דאורייתא de'Oraisa or even if it were דרבנן de'Rabbanan it
doesn't want it to be hinged on דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. That
the גמרא Gemara feels the idea that for רבי יוסי Rav Yose
the way he's explained a minor only owns it because of דרכי
שלום darchei shalom should not be enough to work in this case
of לקט. Leket. So how do we make sense of רבי יוסי
Rav Yose or really rather רבי יוסי Rav Yose the way the
way you know רב חסדא Rav Chisda explains him. So אלא אמר
אביי ella amar Abaye אביי Abaye says let me explain to you
what's going on in the case of the לקט. Leket. It's not
what we thought about the minor taking possession and then transferring to
the father. Here's what's going on. עשוה כמי שהלכו בו נמושות asuha
k'mi she-halkhu bo nemosos דעניי גופייהו מסחי דעתייהו. d'aniyei gufaiyu maschi daiyu.
Okay it's like after you know all of the gatherers went and
נמושות nemosos are the people that like do they're the second round
they're the scavengers they they pick up all the tiny stuff that's
left and after they've been through the field any grain that's left
is free for anyone not just for the poor person because at
that point the עניים aniyim feel like nobody's going to bother going
to a field that the you know second round scavengers have already
been through. So then at that point the לקט Leket stops being
the right for only the poor person. The עניים aniyim themselves figure
we're not even going to bother so now it's free for everyone.
So he says that's what happens here too. דעניי גופייהו מסחי דעתייהו
d'aniyei gufaiyu maschi daiyu and even the עניים aniyim figure forget it
we're not even going to bother. Why?
סברי בריה דהאי מלקט ליה savri b'rei d'hai m'laket lei because they
say look his son is gathering after him what's why you know
why should we go ahead and start collecting? Now that is very
strange I mean as we'll see in one minute in the גמרא
Gemara but first of all if you just think about route you
know whatever there was a lot of people that were doing לקט
Leket just because this guy's got his son why should the עניים
aniyim stop? You know but maybe they feel I don't know maybe
they feel like look whenever he's doing the gathering he's always going
to have his son right there so there's never going to be
anything left for us you know he'll always be the timing get
it way before any of us have a chance. Okay so that's
the reason of רבי יוסי. Rav Yose. רבי יוסי Rav Yose says
it works because because it's really even though you know it would
be owned by the father and the father is a sharecropper not
allowed to take לקט Leket once he has the son following him
the עניים aniyim give it up you know are figure anybody can
have it they're not even going to bother and therefore it's allowed
even if for him as a sharecropper to take it. It's no
longer just the rights of the עניים. aniyim. So the גמרא Gemara
asks the obvious question about this. That would be legal? Says the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רב אדא בר מתנא לאביי amar lei Rav
Adda bar Matna l'Abaye רב אדא בר מתנא Rav Adda bar Matna
says to אביי Abaye וכי מותר לאדם להרביץ ארי בתוך שדהו v'chi
mutar l'adam l'harbitz ari b'toch sadehu כדי שיראו עניים k'dei she-yiru aniyim
So can a person therefore go ahead and have a lion in
his field? Like let's say I'm the בעל הבית baal habayit of
the field and I want to keep all the לקט leket to
myself. So you know what I'm going to do? I'm going to
put some lions, have some lions roaming around in my field. The
עניים aniyim are going to say it's not worth it for us
to risk our lives, they'll go to a different field. So they're
מייאש meyaiesh and now it's מותר muttar for me to take the
לקט. leket. So even if technically that would work, it's not allowed.
Why would רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi allow the son to collect if
fundamentally he doesn't have a right to and in order for this
whole mechanism to then kick in? So אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar
Rava, top of יב עמוד ב, Yud Bet Amud Bet, עשו שאינו
זוכה כזוכה. asu she'eino zocheh kezocheh.
They made somebody who doesn't have rights, the son, who doesn't have
the ability to take possession, as if he takes possession. Okay, meaning
you're right, it's rabbinic. Really, for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi a child
only has, you know, it's only owns it because of דרכי שלום.
darchei shalom. And that would not be enough here for the לקט,
leket, he has to really really own it. But what the rabbis
did is they said, oh, in this case of the לקט, leket,
we will let a minor take really full possession. Why? מאי טעמא?
mai taama? עניים גופייהו ניחא להו. aniyim gufaihu nicha lehu. This is
an institution, you know, a policy that works for everybody. Okay? The
poor people want this policy. כי היכי דכי אגרי
לדידי נילקטו בניי בתריי, ki heichi dechi agri ledidi nilketu banai batrai,
so cause when they get hired to do the gathering of the
grain, they can also use this institution and have their kids do
it as well. Now, if you ask me, I would really question
that because only a small percentage of the עניים aniyim get hired
to gather the grain, and this is so why would it be
in the best interest of all of them because oh they'll benefit
from it as well when they get hired if that won't apply
to ninety percent of them? Also, remember that the we need this
for a case of sharecropping, that was the case that was difficult
here, right, that it's not allowed to be owned directly by the
father. Well, the number of עניים aniyim that have a right that
are that have an opportunity for sharecropping is, you know, much much
smaller. So this is a very questionable idea, but anyway that's how
he explains it. What's worth noting is that it doesn't have to
be דאורייתא, de'oraita, עשו asu meaning it's rabbinically we gave this son
the right to be זוכה. zocher. And the גמרא Gemara is distinguishing
between two types of a rabbinic ownership, right? גזל גמור מדבריהם gezel
gamur midivreichem if it's based on דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, that's what
the גמרא Gemara had a problem with because then the son never
really takes possession. Okay? It's only a type of a way we
operate within דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. It's not because of דרכי שלום
darchei shalom he owns it, like I said before, it's like because
of דרכי שלום darchei shalom we'll consider it like he owns it
even to the point of להוציא בדיינים וגזל, lehotzi bedayanim vegezel, but
fundamentally he doesn't own it. But if here we made a rabbinic
תקנה takkana that a child could take possession then it would work
and that is what we are seeing here. Okay, and that's how
he explains why this works for רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. All right.
ופליגא דרבי חייא בר אבא Upliga deRabbi Hiyya bar Abba דאמר רבי
חייא בר אבא de'amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba אמר רבי יוחנן amar
Rabbi Yochanan לא גדול גדול ממש ולא קטן קטן ממש. lo gadol
gadol mamash velo katan katan mamash. That when we are not talking
here of, you know, שמואל Shmuel that says the reason in the
משנה Mishnah is because the child runs it straight to the father.
All right, so now we have two explanations of the משנה. Mishnah.
Either the child runs it straight to the father, child never took
possession,
or that the child owns it and then it was transferred to
the father. שמואל Shmuel says the first is the explanation of the
משנה, Mishnah, that only works if we're talking about a real minor.
Okay, but that argues on רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Hiyya bar
Abba דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא de'amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לא גדול גדול ממש ולא קטן קטן
ממש. lo gadol gadol mamash velo katan katan mamash. We're not talking
about a real question in the משנה Mishnah that distinguishes between a
מציאה metziah of an adult or a child, אלא גדול הסמוך על
שלחן אביו זה קטן. ella gadol hasamuch al shulchan aviv ze katan.
If you're an adult but you are live at home and supported
by your father, you are for this הלכה halacha of מציאה metziah
considered a minor. קטן ואינו סמוך על שלחן אביו זהו גדול. katan
ve'eino samuch al shulchan aviv zehu gadol. If you have a minor
that basically is out on his own and independent,
then he's considered for this הלכה halacha like an adult and he
keeps the מציאה. metziah. Why? Because for him he says it's not
about the mechanism of the קניינים. kinyanim. For him it's just like
we were sort of saying before about the daughter, you know, about
that you don't want to get the father angry. So for the
daughter it's when the daughter is a minor you don't want to
get the father angry and you want to give him the מציאה
metziah so he doesn't go off and sell off his daughter or
marry off his minor daughter. For the kids, okay, you don't want
to get the father angry, for the boys, excuse me, wow that
was a slip, for the boys you don't want to get the
father angry because if he's supporting them you don't want him to
stop supporting them. What, I put food on the table and I
support you and I give you a room and you can't find
me this diamond that you found? So therefore because he's supporting them
to keep up good relation, therefore therefore he gets to keep their
מציאה. metziah. So that position he says it doesn't matter adult or
minor, it matters whether he's supporting them or not supporting them. Okay?
And that I should say is how we know that שמואל Shmuel
was talking about a different mechanism because this idea means... That yes,
the person owns it, adult or minor who's supported by the father,
they take possession, but then in order to maintain good relations, since
the father is providing for them, it gets transferred to the father.
That's one type of mechanism. That's a mechanism that could work in
the case of לקט. leket. First it gets owned by the person.
שמואל Shmuel who says no, it really is about being a minor
or an adult, then for him the only logic would be and
it's not about this idea being supported or not being supported. There's
no reason we would give it to the father were it not
for this idea that it was picked up and immediately brought to
the father, picked up, you know, never picked up to take possession
for themselves. So that's why you have the two ideas. Either takes
possession and gets transferred and then it's about being supported by the
father or it's about adult and child literally and not being supported,
and then the only reason it would be owned by the father
would be because the kid runs it to the father. Okay. Now,
last part of the משנה. mishna. Okay, מציאת עבדו ושפחתו העברים הרי
הוא של עצמן. metziat avdo v'shifchato haivrim harei hu shel atzman.
By the Hebrew slaves they get to keep it. Now, because why?
אמאי amai says the גמרא. Gemara. לא יהא אלא פועל. lo yehe
ella poel. They should be no worse than a פועל. poel. I
mean the person owns them more than you do like a hired
hand. A hired hand is more of a contract you could think,
you know, by עבד עברי eved ivri you own him for his
labor, so it's much more of an ownership. And we know that
by a hired hand you get the
מציאה. metziah. ותניא ותנן בברייתא מציאת פועל לעצמו v'tanya v'tunan b'raisa metziat
poel leatzmo that if a פועל poel finds a lost object he
gets to keep it. במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is
that true? בזמן שאין נכחשים עמי מהיום עד היום bizman she'ein nichashim
imi meh-hayom ad hayom if you say like hoe for me, weed
for me, so then when he picks up the מציאה metziah he's
off the clock. He has to pay you for taking that two
minutes off the clock, but then he is clearly not doing what
you hired him for. He's operating as an independent, you know, on
his own, and he gets to keep it. אבל אמר לו עשה
עמי מלאכה היום, aval amar lo asei imi melacha hayom, but if
he says to him, you know, work for me the whole day,
the whole day, whatever I tell you, you know, any work you're
doing is mine. So there's no off the clock. He's always on
the clock. So in that case מציאתו לבעל הבית. metziato l'baal habayis.
When he picks it up it gets owned by the בעל הבית
baal habayis because he's always on the clock and therefore when he
picks it up he's picking it up for the בעל הבית. baal
habayis. That's a מלאכה. melacha. All right, but what you do see,
so you see there that an עבד, eved, somebody a Hebrew slave,
you know, you own them for everything. So any work you want
them to do, they're not, owning a slave, you know, the sense
of ownership doesn't mean you're contracting for a particular job. And therefore
a slave is always on the clock, so it should always, even
a Hebrew slave, a Hebrew slave, and therefore it should always be
owned by the owner. So the גמרא Gemara says
where are we?
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן הכא בעבד נוקב מרגליות
עסקינן שאין רבו רוצה לשנותו למלאכה אחרת. amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan hacha b'eved nokeiv margaliyot askinan she'ein rabbo rotzeh l'shanos
l'melacha acheres. We're talking about a slave that has a very, you
know, specialized skill. He's able to drill holes in pearls. And that
type of a for that type of a of a slave, you
do not want him to do anything else. And if that slave
were to stop, you know, going and drilling holes in the pearls
which is worth, I don't know, a thousand dollars an hour and
go decide to take out the trash, then he'd be off the
clock. Then you would be able to demand from the slave you
just, you know, pay me back at the basis of a thousand
dollars an hour for going and taking out the trash. Okay? And
because you that is not what I wanted you to do, you
have to pay me back. So
therefore if the slave actually then sees a מציאה metziah that's worth
more than the time off, a diamond, all right, he would and
he picks it up to keep it for himself, he would be
off the clock as soon as he stopped drilling the holes in
the pearl. He'd pay the master back for the time off from
drilling the holes in the pearl, and he would keep it for
himself. All right. So it's interesting there though because you know as
opposed to the case of the hired hand where the contract is
only is to do this, to weed, to hoe, whatever. Here you
do own the slave for everything, but because you say, you designate
I only want you to do this, anytime he's doing something else
he's off the clock, he pays you for his time off, but
ultimately he's on his own. Okay where are
we?
Okay. רבא אמר במגביה מציאה עם מלאכתו עסקינן. Rava amar b'magbia metziah
im melachto askinan. That the slave is actually picking up the מציאה
metziah while he is doing something else. So yes, you've hired him
for everything and you tell him, you know, right now he's hoeing
or whatever, and this slave. But as he's hoeing and as he's
like, you know, and as he's I don't know let's say he's
collecting garbage, better example. You tell him to go pick up all
the garbage in the yard and as he's picking up garbage there's
a diamond there, so he picks it up in the same act
that he's picking up for garbage. Okay. So in that case, you
know, he is considered to be, you know. operating independent of the
job he is doing for you and not on your clock. I
find that a little bit harder because at the end of the
day he's still a slave, so isn't all of his labor ultimately
your labor? Isn't everything he does? But I guess the point is
that since his job is to pick up garbage and he was,
only the picking up garbage is defined as the labor he's doing
for you and anything that he's doing at the same time he
is not considered to be done for you. It's an interesting distinction.
Okay. רב פפא אמר כגון ששכרו ללקט מציאות. Rav Pappa amar kegon
shesecharo lilaket metzi'os. Okay, so Rav Pappa
says no, no, no. The case where if you hire a laborer
without designation, the מציאות metzi'os go to you, that is not a
case, you misunderstood that. Okay, that is not a case that you
just hired him generically. All right? He actually was hired to go
ahead and to gather up מציאות. metzi'os. What's the case? והיכי דמי
דאקפי אגמי בחברי? V'heichi dami d'akfei agmi b'chavrei? Let's say, you know,
the waters overflowed and a lot of fish are now on the
shore and you hire him to go ahead and to pick up
all the fish. Okay? Only that, so it's only that case that
if he finds something it goes to the owner, so you completely
misunderstood the ברייתא braisa when it says if you just say עשה
עמי מלאכה asei imi melacha generically it goes to the, it goes
to the person who hired, that actually is incorrect. Generically it would,
the person would get to keep it. It's only if they are
specifically, it's totally against the language of the ברייתא, braisa, what can
I do? But only if they're specifically being hired to collect מציאות
metzi'os do the מציאות metzi'os go to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayis.
All right, but that doesn't exactly explain by a slave, because, you
know, again like you would think that everything a slave does is
for the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, but that's what he's telling you
is not the case. That you know, you get your orders at
the beginning of the day and you never have this idea that
everything I do is for the owners. It's a function about what
we agreed on and there's, you know, and even you cannot make
stipulate and say any act you do is always on my behalf.
All right, so that's a nice limiting of it but it doesn't
really work the language of the ברייתא braisa anyway. Okay, last case.
האי שפחה היכי דמי? Hai shifcha heichi dami? What's the case of
the שפחה shifcha where we say that it is, the Hebrew maidservant,
the Hebrew, the Jewish one, that it goes to the owner? Okay?
אי דאייתי שתי שערות, Ei d'aisi shtei se'aros, if she has two
pubic hairs she's an adult, so then מאי בעיא גביה, mai ba'ya
gabei, then what's she doing under his, you know, in his servitude?
Okay? Because as soon as she becomes an adult she goes free.
That's the הלכה halacha about a Jewish Hebrew slave girl.
ואי דלא אייתי שתי שערות, V'ei d'lo aisi shtei se'aros, if she's
not an adult, אי דאיתיה לאב, ei d'is'leh l'av, if her father
is alive, דאבוה הואי, d'avuha havai, we just said in the משנה
mishna that, you know, a, that things that are found by a
minor boy and girl go to the father. Now the, you could
say maybe that's if he hasn't sold her as a slave, once
he's sold her transfers to the owner. Interestingly the גמרא Gemara understands
that that is not the case, you know, especially since the reason
you want the father to get the מציאות metzi'os is so he
doesn't sell her, in this case he's already sold her as a
slave. But the גמרא Gemara thinks that even in this case the
father would get it, so why is it going to the master?
ואי דליתיה לאב, V'ei d'leisleh l'av, if the father died, תיפוק במיתת
האב, tipok b'misas ha'av, she should be freed from the master with
the death of the father. דאמר ריש לקיש, D'amar Reish Lakish, because
Reish Lakish says אמה עברייה קנתה עצמה במיתת האב מרשות האדון, Amah
Ivriyah kanta atzmah b'misas ha'av mereshus ha'adon, that a Hebrew slave girl
gets her own freedom when her father dies, she is freed from
the master from the others being owned by the owner. מקל וחומר,
Mikal vachomer, based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. The קל וחומר
kal vachomer is that if, you know, she's freed from the control
of the father then certainly she should be freed from the control
of the master. So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי יוחנן סבר דריש
לקיש? V'Rabbi Yochanan savar Reish Lakish? Why are you bothering me with
that? Says the גמרא, Gemara, Reish Lakish's position was contradicted, was, you
know,
we disproved Reish Lakish so we don't hold of it, so we
could be talking in our משנה mishna that the father died. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay fine, but נימא מהא נמי תהוי תיובתא?
neima me'ha nami tehvei siyuvta? I want to know is this משנה
mishna also a proof against Reish Lakish because the only way to
explain this משנה mishna is that the father died and that would
prove that the girl is still a slave even after the father
died. לא, Lo, says the גמרא Gemara not necessarily. לעולם דאיתיה לאב,
Le'olam d'is'leh l'av, really the father is alive. Okay, so why does
it say that it goes to the master? ומהי הרי הן שלהן,
u'mai harei hen shelahen, excuse me, לא לעולם דאיתיה לאב ומהי הרי
הן שלהן. lo le'olam d'is'leh l'av u'mai harei hen shelahen.
Oh
I'm sorry I misinterpreted the earlier גמרא, Gemara, right, the case by
the slave I got confused because of the whole previous discussion. The
case by the slave girl is that they get to keep their
own מציאות, metzi'os, right, not that it goes to the master. All
right. So the גמרא Gemara is saying like I don't get it,
right? What does it mean that she gets, why does the משנה
mishna say she gets to keep it? It should go to the
father. All right, so not that it should go to the master
but it should go, why should she get to keep it? Don't
we teach that it goes to the father? So the גמרא Gemara
says yes that is what it means. ומהי הרי הן שלהן U'mai
harei hen shelahen means that. It doesn't go to the master. She
keeps it, and after she keeps it, then the הלכה Halacha kicks
in that it goes to the father. Okay, so again, the משנה
Mishnah says that the findings of a slave Hebrew slaves are their
own, the גמרא Gemara challenges this about the whole idea about a
פועל Poel and figures out why this is true in the case
of slaves, of maybe it's only by pearls and who knows what
that they are, you know, but whatever it is, slaves are their
own. Then it speaks about what is the case of, you know,
of of of the slave woman girl, okay, obviously it would have
to be a girl, and if it's a girl, because you know,
that's the הלכה Halacha that only you can only own a Hebrew
slave who's a girl, and if it's a girl, then it's she
doesn't keep it herself, it should go to the father. And in
the end the גמרא Gemara says that's actually correct. That's what it
means. It means the master doesn't get it, she owns it herself,
and once she owns it herself then the הלכה Halacha transfers it
to the father. Okay, last case, מציאת אשתו, Metziat ishto, the wife
that he divorced, she keeps, so the גמרא Gemara says, גירשה פשיטא,
Gerashah peshita, she's divorced, of course she keeps it. נו הכא במאי
עסקינן במגורשת ואינה מגורשת. No hacha bemai askinan bimgureshet veina megureshet. There's
a question whether she's divorced, he threw the גט, Get, they didn't
know whether it actually got close enough to her to be considered
that she's divorced or not. דאמר רבי זירא אמר שמואל, Damar Rabbi
Zeira amar Shmuel, וכל מקום שאמרו חכמים מגורשת ואינה מגורשת, Vechol makom
sheamru chachamim megureshet veina megureshet, בעלה חייב במזונותיה. Baalah chayav bimezonoteha.
If she's questionably divorced or not, the husband cannot take advantage of
that, he still has all of his obligations to her, he has
to provide her with housing, with food and all of that until
she's definitely divorced.
טעמא מאי אמרו רבנן מציאת אשה לבעלה, Taama mai amru rabanan metziat
ishah lebaalah, why did they normally say the the it goes to
the husband? כדי שלא תהא לה איבה, Kedei shelo tehei lah eivah,
so he shouldn't, you
know, it shouldn't be enmity between them. He shouldn't be upset, I
provide for you and then you go ahead and you earn and
you don't give it to me. So to make it, they make
it reciprocal for nice relationships. In this case הכא איכא איבה ואיבה,
Hacha ika eivah veivah, here there's tremendous enmity. He's in the process
of divorcing her. So, if he's in the process of divorcing her
and the גט Get and she's questionably divorced, he cannot get out
of his obligations to her, but she does not have any reciprocal
obligations to him because because already they're in the process of divorce,
so it's there would not there's no need for him for you
know for for to try to prevent ill will. Of course as
we know now of course with the whole issues of עגונה, Agunah,
sadly there's a lot of need to prevent ill will, but whatever
that was not the reality in the גמרא. Gemara.